<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A faithful warning, with good advice from Israel's God, to Englands King, and his council that they may wisely improve this little inch of time which the God of their life as yet affords unto them, before the day of their approaching misery come upon them. Which may serve as a caution to all others in authority within the nation. Sounded through one of the mourners in Sion, known by the name of Martin Mason.</title>
            <author>Mason, Martin, fl. 1650-1676.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89638</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M927</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202015</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99899666</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99899666</idno>
            <idno type="VID">135059</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89638)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 135059)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2431:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A faithful warning, with good advice from Israel's God, to Englands King, and his council that they may wisely improve this little inch of time which the God of their life as yet affords unto them, before the day of their approaching misery come upon them. Which may serve as a caution to all others in authority within the nation. Sounded through one of the mourners in Sion, known by the name of Martin Mason.</title>
                  <author>Mason, Martin, fl. 1650-1676.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 20, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Robert Wilson, at the sign of the Black spread-Eagle and Wind-Mill in Martins l' Grand,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1660]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publication date suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>The word "approaching" is enclosed within square brackets on title page.</note>
                  <note>Last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Another edition has "vvarning" on title page.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Repentance --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:135059:1"/>
            <p>A FAITHFUL WARNING, WITH GOOD ADVICE FROM ISRAEL'S GOD, TO Englands KING, AND HIS COUNCIL; That they may wiſely improve this little Inch of time which the God of their Life as yet affords unto them, before the Day of their [approaching] Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry come upon them.</p>
            <p>Which may ſerve as a Caution to all others in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority within the Nation.</p>
            <p>Sounded through one of the Mourners in <hi>Sion,</hi> known by the name of <hi>Martin Maſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hear ye, and give ear, be not proud, for the Lord hath ſpoken.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Wilſon,</hi> at the ſign of the <hi>Black ſpread-Eagle</hi> and <hi>Wind-Mill</hi> in <hi>Martins l' Grand.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:135059:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:135059:2"/>
            <head>A FAITHFVL WARNING, WITH GOOD ADVICE FROM <hi>Iſrael's GOD,</hi> to <hi>England's KING</hi> AND HIS COUNCIL, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ehold, <hi>to obey</hi> is better <hi>than ſacrifice;</hi> and <hi>to hearken,</hi> is better <hi>
                  <hi>than the fat of Rams.</hi> Liſten</hi> therefore, and encline your Ear, be <hi>attentive,</hi> and read without preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice: For the Righteous God hath laid it upon me, <hi>once more</hi> to Warn the Men in Authority, the Rulers of this Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; even from him that fits upon <hi>the Throne,</hi> to the infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior Governors of the people, that they ceaſe from their iniquities, and fear the living God.</p>
            <p>Know ye therefore, large hath the love of God been towards you, and with wonderful loving-kindneſs hath he viſited you; his patience verily is beyond expreſſion; for your iniquities have highly provoked him: How
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:135059:3"/>many <hi>Warnings</hi> hath he given you, all which hitherto have been but little regarded by you? O let his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Witneſs in all your Conſciences ariſe, and it will te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie the wonderful Mercies of your Maker towards you. Have you anſwered the End and Requirings of the Lord from you, in his Overturning your Enemies for you, and thus ſetling the Government of the Nations upon you? Came you not in without any <hi>Conqueſt?</hi> Can you juſtly glory in your own ſtrength, that it was your own Arm that hath done this for you? Was it your own Valour that vanquiſhed your enemies? Or is it not the hand of the Lord that hath thus exalted you, and aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them that had the Government before you? I ſay, Have you anſwered the Requirings of the Lord? Let his Witneſs be awakened, and ariſe in all your conſciences, and anſwer to me. Did he lay no injunction upon you when his heart was enclined to exalt you? Did he not enjoin you to <hi>amendment of Life,</hi> to <hi>ſhew mercy,</hi> to <hi>glorifie your Maker,</hi> to be <hi>Patterns of Piety,</hi> and <hi>good Examples to the People;</hi> to let <hi>Mercy, Truth</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs live</hi> amongſt you, and be exerciſed by you towards the people who are now fallen under you; to ſhew favour to the <hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,</hi> to help the <hi>helpleſs,</hi> and to remedie the <hi>wrongs</hi> of the <hi>poor</hi> and <hi>needy;</hi> to ſuppreſs <hi>Vice</hi> and <hi>Vanity</hi> in <hi>Court, City</hi> and <hi>Countrey;</hi> to be <hi>a terror to evil doers, and a praiſe and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement unto them that do well?</hi> And have none of you in the time of your <hi>diſtreſs</hi> promiſed to the <hi>Lord</hi> the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of <hi>theſe things?</hi> Did the Lord (I ſay) ſet you upon <hi>the Throne,</hi> and thus reſtore you to <hi>outward Dignity,</hi> when you ſeemed to be going down into the place of forgetfulneſs, when you had little hopes to have ſuch a Day without a ſecret enjoining to theſe things? Did he give you the <hi>deſire</hi> of <hi>your hearts,</hi> onely to be revenged of your Enemies, and to aggravate and multiply the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of <hi>his People?</hi> If his Witneſs were awakened in your Conſciences, ſurely you would ſay, <hi>Let God be juſtified, and ſinful man condemned?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:135059:3"/>
            <p>Oh my Friends, how haue you trifled away God's pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious time, and your own <hi>Deliverance!</hi> How hath <hi>Vice</hi> and <hi>Vanity</hi> abounded in the <hi>Nation</hi> ſince the <hi>Day</hi> of <hi>your Exaltation</hi> in <hi>England?</hi> Does not <hi>Iniquity, Pride</hi> and <hi>Luxury</hi> Lord it <hi>amongſt you</hi> both in <hi>Court, City</hi> and <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey,</hi> with an <hi>impudent forehead?</hi> Is not <hi>Prophaneneſs</hi> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced <hi>by you?</hi> Are not the <hi>wicked</hi> and <hi>ungodly</hi> had in eſtimation <hi>with you?</hi> Do not the <hi>unrighteous</hi> boaſt in <hi>your ſtrength?</hi> And hath not <hi>your Horn</hi> exalted them through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the <hi>Nation?</hi> Are not the <hi>Merchants of Babylon</hi> grown familiar <hi>with you,</hi> and the <hi>Sons of Belial</hi> advanced <hi>by you?</hi> Or is there any people receive ſuch favour from you as the <hi>Rotten Intereſt,</hi> who are now <hi>indulged by you?</hi> What's become of <hi>Sion?</hi> Are you acquainted with her? Do you miniſter <hi>true comfort</hi> to her? Is ſhe <hi>advanced</hi> or <hi>diſcountenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced</hi> in <hi>your Court</hi> and the <hi>Kingdom?</hi> Are you <hi>true Subjects</hi> to <hi>Sion</hi>'s <hi>King?</hi> Rules he as <hi>Caeſar</hi> in the <hi>Kingdom of your hearts?</hi> Do you know Him, and pay <hi>Tribute</hi> to Him? Do you ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve His <hi>Laws, Statutes</hi> and <hi>Ordinances?</hi> Do you own His <hi>Light</hi> in all <hi>your Conſciences</hi> to be <hi>your Leader, Judge</hi> and <hi>Lawgiver?</hi> Oh happy were <hi>England</hi> had ſhe ſuch a <hi>King,</hi> and happy were <hi>Englands King</hi> had he ſuch <hi>Counſellors?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But alas! alas! <hi>Sion</hi> is in the <hi>Duſt,</hi> and no man regards her; her <hi>Enemies</hi> now ſeem to be too many for her, and make themſelves merry over her: They who ſhould be as <hi>Nurſing-Fathers</hi> to her, withdraw their affections from her; ſhe ſits weeping in the <hi>Houſe of Mourning,</hi> for the <hi>miſery</hi> that is coming upon this <hi>People;</hi> while the <hi>drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards of Ephraim</hi> tunn themſelves with Wine, and intoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate their Brains with <hi>ſtrong Drink;</hi> and the <hi>greedy She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pherds</hi> devour the <hi>ſilly Flock,</hi> and the <hi>luſtful ones</hi> love to have <hi>it ſo;</hi> while the <hi>Prieſt</hi> and <hi>People</hi> conſpire together againſt the <hi>Lord</hi> and his <hi>Annointed Jewels,</hi> to ſtop the <hi>Mouth</hi> of <hi>Truth,</hi> and fill their priſons with innocent peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; yet can they not center here, <hi>Mordecai</hi>'s <hi>Seed</hi> is a great Mote in the <hi>Devils Diſh,</hi> which the <hi>old Dragon</hi> ſeeks to devour by ſome <hi>unrighteous Decree</hi> from <hi>Caeſar:</hi> For the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:135059:4"/>Crown they count ſure of their fide, and that's the <hi>top<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone</hi> of <hi>Egypts ſtrength.</hi> To the <hi>Refuge of Lyes</hi> they now betake themſelves, and by their <hi>Majeſtical Craft</hi> do abuſe both their <hi>Prince</hi> and the <hi>Countrey, Cum Privilegio,</hi> and all for want of a good Underſtanding.</p>
            <p>For would but <hi>Caeſar</hi> and his <hi>Council</hi> ſtop their Ear to their <hi>Trencher-Chaplains,</hi> and the alluring inchantments of ſuch <hi>devouring Monſters,</hi> who ſeek to ſubvert and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Innocent: I ſay, would but the King and his Council once be perſwaded to come into <hi>calmneſs,</hi> and take counſel of <hi>God's ORACLE,</hi> the <hi>Light</hi> in their <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences,</hi> and by it be guided, how ſoon would the <hi>dark, miſty Fogs</hi> of <hi>Egypt</hi> and her <hi>Magicians,</hi> be diſpel'd, and driven back into the <hi>bottomleſs pit.</hi> No <hi>croaking Frogs</hi> durſt then come forth to abuſe the <hi>Honor</hi> of a <hi>Prince;</hi> nor wound his <hi>Reputation,</hi> by enticing him to <hi>Cruelty;</hi> nor ſcrue his <hi>Prerogative</hi> above the Peoples <hi>Tranquility:</hi> For the End of all Government appointed by God, next to his <hi>Glory,</hi> is <hi>the good of the People</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Salus Populi Suprema Lex.</note>. For the <hi>great God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth ſo loved the world, that he ſent his Son a Light into the world, not to deſtroy mens lives, but to ſave them;</hi> yet to puniſh the <hi>evil-doer</hi> according to the nature of his <hi>Crime,</hi> but not with <hi>Impriſonment, Death</hi> or <hi>Baniſhment</hi> for every ſmall offence, much leſs for that wch is no offence at all.</p>
            <p>For what ever is not <hi>Malum in ſe,</hi> an evil in it ſelf, ought rather to be <hi>indulged,</hi> than ſo <hi>ſeverely puniſhed.</hi> For a man to be covered with his <hi>Hat</hi> before <hi>Authority,</hi> is no <hi>evil in it ſelf,</hi> though falſely ſo counted by the <hi>evil ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious one;</hi> nor for a man to be honeſtly imployed upon your <hi>Popiſh Feſtival dayes,</hi> is not ſinful or evil in it ſelf, though ſinners raſhly ſo judge it, and wrongfully impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the Righteous for bearing their <hi>Teſtimony</hi> againſt it. Nor is the Conſcientious refuſing of an <hi>Oath,</hi> an <hi>Evil in it ſelf;</hi> for <hi>Chriſt</hi> the <hi>Oath of God</hi> expreſly commandeth, <hi>Swear not at all,</hi> and therefore it is (muſt of neceſſity be) an evil in him that puniſhes the <hi>Innocent</hi> for not violating
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:135059:4"/>the <hi>Law of God,</hi> with impriſonment [at pleaſute] and loſe of Eſtate. Far be it from the <hi>Sons of Innocency</hi> to <hi>Plott</hi> or <hi>Confederate</hi> againſt the <hi>Perſon</hi> of a <hi>Prince;</hi> and as far be it from them by ſtooping to the <hi>Will of Man,</hi> to violate the <hi>Law of the Living God;</hi> and it ſhould be far from the <hi>Prince</hi> to puniſh ſuch a People for not tranſgreſſing the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand</hi> of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> And did not our Adverſaries anſwer us with more <hi>raſhneſs, rage</hi> and <hi>raw Arguments,</hi> than <hi>good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning,</hi> concerning our <hi>not Swearing,</hi> if <hi>Sic volo ſic jubeo, ſtet pro ratione voluntas,</hi> were not too predominant with them, we ſhould not in that particular receive ſuch hard mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure from them.</p>
            <p>Man placed in <hi>Authority,</hi> ſhould <hi>Rule for God,</hi> and ought to have his Eye within his Head, his minde (I mean) ſtaid upon the <hi>Light of Iſrael,</hi> God's Witneſs pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in his Soul, and read and meditate in that Book day and night, even all the dayes of his life: And this is not <hi>durus ſermo,</hi> a hard ſaying, but a <hi>well-doing.</hi> This was that made <hi>David</hi> honourable, <hi>and a man after God's own heart,</hi> and <hi>Solomon</hi> his Son, the wiſeſt King that ever ſate upon a Throne.</p>
            <p>O that <hi>England</hi>'s <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Council</hi> would <hi>ſummo co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natu,</hi> ſeek after true Wiſdom, which if any man want, let him ask it of God; the way to find it, is to beg for it, of him alone who hath the diſpoſal of it; the King of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> the God of <hi>Solomon,</hi> who dwells in the Light, <hi>which enlightens every man that comes into the world:</hi> His <hi>Wiſdom</hi> is to be prized more than Gold, ſhe is of more worth to a <hi>Prince</hi> than Pearls or Rubies; Cabinets of Jewels are not to be compared to her, and gliſtering Diamonds come too ſhort of her; the Tongue of <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Angels</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſufficiently commend her; the <hi>High</hi> and <hi>Lofty</hi> are not worthy of her: 'Tis the <hi>Sons of Innocency</hi> that have Right unto her, and the <hi>Children of the Day</hi> that are ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by her: <hi>Rough Eſau</hi>'s <hi>Birth</hi> is a ſtranger to her, and muſt not have the Honor to be acquainted with her; that brood for a meſs of Pottage would ſell their Birt-right,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:135059:5"/>and abandon her: 'Tis onely <hi>ſmooth Jacob,</hi> or <hi>Valiant Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> who wreſtles with <hi>his God,</hi> as a Prince (who in his heart affects her, and fixes the delight of his ſoul upon her, and as the Jewel of his God does honour her) that is worthy of her: On him muſt the bleſſing come.</p>
            <p>And have not <hi>England</hi>'s <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Senators</hi> need of ſuch a Counſellor? Is not this <hi>WISDOM</hi> worthy to be inquired of by them? Or are they wiſe enough to do wel without her? The Wiſdom of this World is not to be compared unto her.</p>
            <q>
               <l>For if that muddy thing</l>
               <l>Could honour <hi>England</hi>'s King;</l>
               <l>He and his Council have a Spring.</l>
               <l>But that poor Toy</l>
               <l>Gives no true Joy:</l>
               <l>'Tis Wiſdom from above,</l>
               <l>Comes from the God of Love,</l>
               <l>That ſarisfies the humble mind,</l>
               <l>And doth the Proud in Fetters bind,</l>
               <l>Come then O <hi>England</hi>'s KING,</l>
               <l>Drink at pure Wiſdoms Spring,</l>
               <l>And you his Gouncil turn your eyes</l>
               <l>To <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Light, if you'l be wiſe.</l>
            </q>
            <p>For know this from the Lord, never had King more need of wiſe Councel, nor ſuch a Council more need of a wiſe King, then you have at this ſeaſon. Alas poor Mortals! whither are you poſting in the dark? Hold in the Reins, and curb thoſe pamper'd Steeds that carry you ſo ſwiftly (as it were on the wings of the wind) down into the Gulf of endleſs miſery. Stop poor men; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount, diſmount, ride on no further; repoſe your ſelves, and deliberate a little ſeaſon; ſee if you can come to a
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:135059:5"/>a little Reſt; Retire your ſelves within, come into your <hi>Bed-Chamber;</hi> commune with your own hearts, and be <hi>ſtill:</hi> Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten, and incline your ear to that <hi>ſtill Voice</hi> of the <hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous God,</hi> that gently calls upon you in your <hi>Conſciences,</hi> and counſels you to <hi>ſhew mercy,</hi> and <hi>uſe moderation,</hi> that reproves for ſin in the heart. Come I ſay, to the <hi>Croſs of Chriſt,</hi> O ye <hi>Great Council</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and all that are in Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in this Nation, and know a bridle to your <hi>Luſts:</hi> Learn of the <hi>Lamb of God,</hi> and of his <hi>Light</hi> which he hath placed in your <hi>Conſciences</hi>) to be <hi>meek and lowly;</hi> let your minds <hi>ſink down</hi> unto, and <hi>center in</hi> the <hi>Seed of Life,</hi> which lies low <hi>in you</hi> all, that <hi>Babe of Glory</hi> who lies in the <hi>Manger,</hi> and all this time hath had no room in the <hi>Inne.</hi> Mind (I ſay) the breathings of that <hi>Innocent Babe</hi> within you; obſerve the ſweet ſound of his Voice who never ſinn'd, who yet calmly reproves you when you ſin againſt him; obey his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand; <hi>his yoake is eaſie, and his burthen light;</hi> he will counſel you to part with nothing that is worth your poſſeſſing; <hi>Vice</hi> and <hi>Vanity,</hi> with all <hi>manner of iniquity</hi> and <hi>luſt,</hi> are loathſome to him, for theſe he is angry with you; yet in the Light he is willing to be <hi>reconciled to you:</hi> Lo, how he calls upon you in his love, and ſhews pity towards you: Ah how like a <hi>tender Father</hi> does he bear with you! How long hath his <hi>Mercy</hi> ſpared you! How unwilling is he to enter into judgement with you, would you but turn unto him at his <hi>reproof!</hi> Nothing will he require <hi>of you,</hi> but what would be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding good <hi>for you,</hi> (which indeed is a duty ſies upon you, and were you but willing, he would give you <hi>Power</hi> to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form) <hi>to honour him that made you, by believing and walking in the Light.</hi> Believe in him who in the ſecret of your hearts lets you ſee when you are entering into, or have committed any ſin, or are hatching miſchief in your hearts againſt the Innocent; Believe that <hi>Voice</hi> to be the <hi>Voice of God,</hi> the <hi>Light in your Conſciences,</hi> and give up your ſelves unto it, and be guided by it; Keep friendſhip with it; Forſake all that which is reproved by it, and follow the <hi>Light</hi> whither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever it leads you; if it lead you through the <hi>Croſs</hi> to your <hi>carnal minds,</hi> out of <hi>ſin,</hi> out of <hi>mire</hi> and <hi>dirt</hi> into the path
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:135059:6"/>of <hi>purity</hi> and <hi>holineſs;</hi> out of <hi>Paſſion,</hi> into <hi>Patience;</hi> out of <hi>Pride,</hi> into <hi>true Humility;</hi> out of <hi>Hatred,</hi> into <hi>hearty Love:</hi> (O <hi>bleſſed Change,</hi> if you were willing to be changed by it!) out of <hi>Revenge,</hi> to a <hi>free forgiveneſs;</hi> out of <hi>Folly</hi> or <hi>Worldly Wit,</hi> into <hi>Divine Wiſdom:</hi> Who would not go after ſuch a <hi>Guide!</hi> Who would not ſerve ſuch a <hi>Noble Lord,</hi> that ſends not his <hi>ſervant</hi> upon any ſervice by himſelf alone, but goes alongwth him, or rather before him, and is a <hi>Guide</hi> unto him! What he commands him to do, he onely requires the <hi>heart,</hi> a <hi>willing mind,</hi> and does the <hi>thing himſelf,</hi> or gives <hi>power</hi> to <hi>perform it.</hi> Such a <hi>Lord</hi> is <hi>Iſrael's God;</hi> all the gods of the <hi>Heathen</hi> are not to be compared unto him. He calls, <hi>My Son, give me thy heart;</hi> and, <hi>Come unto me all yee that are weary and heavy laden with the load of your iniquities, and I will give you eaſe.</hi> O <hi>Golden Promiſe</hi> of a gracious God! which he freely performs to all his people: <hi>To as many as receive him,</hi> (and believe in him, and are willing to be guided by him, to leave Luſt, and walk in the Light, which makes war againſt it) <hi>he gives pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to become the ſons of God;</hi> [mark] to theſe he gives power to become the Sons of God. <hi>O bountiful God! O merciful King of Saints! worthy of all Honour, Glory, and everlaſting Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: Thou gives power to thoſe that have rebelled againſt Thee, and have been Traytors to Thee, to be at peace with Thee, to be reconciled to thee, and receive pardon from thee; yea, to become thy Children upon their ſubmiſſion to thee: 'Tis thou Righteous God, works all our good works for us, and in us, and then accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt of thine own.</hi> Here is a pattern for all Princes and great ones to forgive your Enemies. O! let <hi>Revenge</hi> live no longer in you, but be buried in the grave of eternal forgetfulneſs; Let the <hi>Immortal Witneſs of God</hi> ariſe in the <hi>Court of your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> that <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Innocency</hi> may live, and the contrary Nature dye.</p>
            <p>'Tis time, yea high time for every <hi>Individual</hi> of you to turn your minds to God's gracious Gift, his <hi>Light in your Conſciences,</hi> that all <hi>Arbitrary Power</hi> and <hi>Oppreſſion</hi> may be turned out of your hearts, that <hi>bitterneſs of ſpirit</hi> may no longer live, or burn in your breaſts. O beware, beware of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:135059:6"/>the <hi>Spirit of Revenge,</hi> and down with all <hi>Idolatry,</hi> and <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous Superſtition;</hi> for <hi>Dagon</hi> cannot, nor muſt not ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Ark of God.</hi> O come to the Grace of God in your own particulars, you that are the <hi>Council</hi> to <hi>Englands King,</hi> &amp; you inferior Officers; come I ſay, &amp; receive the <hi>wholeſom Inſtructions</hi> of that <hi>Divine ORACLE</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in your <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences</hi> which brings Salvation with it (to all that are willing to be ſaved by it, and love the <hi>Light</hi> better than their <hi>Luſt</hi>) which beats down the Devil's Kingdom, and teaches, and will teach you (be you but willing to be taught by it) to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>ungodlineſs and all worldly luſts, Pride, Arrogancy, Scorn, Frowardneſs, Covetouſneſs, vain-idle-talk, Drunkenneſs, Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Paſſion, Cruelty, Luxury, and all Superfluity of Naughti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Revenge, Hatred, Malice;</hi> theſe are all Ungodlineſs, and makes that man who lives in the commitment of them, unlike to God. You being willing to bear the Reproof of the Lord for theſe, and what other ſins your hearts are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted to, and in love withall; you being willing to part with theſe Whoriſh Lovers, baſe Luſts, who have ſtoln away your hearts, and ſeparated you from your God; the <hi>Light of God</hi> in your <hi>Conſciences</hi> which teſtifies againſt theſe things that they are evil, will beget in you a diſlike and loathing of all theſe filthy noyſome luſts which defile the ſoul, becauſe they grieve the <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> of the <hi>Righteous God;</hi> &amp; then you wil ſee every ſin (as it is) to be ugly; <hi>Pride</hi> to be an <hi>Evil Seed,</hi> which the <hi>Enemy</hi> hath ſown in the heart; <hi>Riotouſneſs, Luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Luſt, Revenge, Swearing, Drunkenneſs,</hi> and the like, to be all <hi>fruits</hi> of the <hi>Devil's begetting,</hi> generated in the heart of man in the time of darkneſs and ignorance: Then ſhall you ſee the wrath of God due to that Nature which delights to wallow in ſuch <hi>miry wickedneſs;</hi> ſo ſhall you come to know the <hi>holy Fear</hi> planted within you, that when the Tempter comes to aſſault you, he cannot enter upon you. The <hi>faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Souldier</hi> and <hi>follower of the Lamb</hi> is kept upon his <hi>Watch;</hi> he ſees the <hi>Thief</hi> comes to rob and ſteal the heart from the Lord, but conſents not to the <hi>Thief,</hi> but reſiſts the Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, who then flies from him; <hi>He dares not do ſuch a wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:135059:7"/>and ſin againſt his God.</hi> This would be a bleſſed Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and happy are all they that are found therein.</p>
            <p>And verily my friends, it is high time that you meet the Lord by unfeigned Repentance, and forſaking of your ſins; for his wrath is kindled againſt you, becauſe <hi>your hearts are not right before the Lord.</hi> How long, Ah how long have you ſought to hide your Counſels from the Lord, and to <hi>beguile the Children of the Light,</hi> and deceive the Simple with fair ſugred words, when the poiſon of Aſps hath been under your tongue! but the Sons of Wiſdom, the true Children of the Day have not been deceived by you.</p>
            <p>Think you the Lord is well pleaſed with you? Can you be perſwaded that he ſees you not, or that he reveals not your vanity and ſubtilty to his Seed? Or do you believe that he winks at your wickedneſs, and will not viſit for all your iniquity? O be not ſo fooliſh and unwiſe; for verily ſuch as you ſow, ſuch ſhall you reap; and if you perſiſt in your obſtinacy againſt the Lord, and withſtand the Day of your Viſitation; if you will ſtill run on in the race of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, and caſt the Teſtimony of his Law-behind you; if you will let your minds ſtill purſue the pleaſures of this world, and prefer the tranſitory things of this life before your ſouls Peace; if you will count worldly gain to be godlineſs; if you will ſpeak ſmooth things to your King, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfully, and counſel him to rejoice and make merry over God's Witneſs in his Conſcience, as if he ſhould never come to judgement; if you will lend your ear to the <hi>Charming Sorceries</hi> of the <hi>Hireling Prieſts,</hi> the <hi>Engliſh Rabbies,</hi> who now are doting upon <hi>Romes Traſh</hi> and <hi>Trumperies,</hi> who <hi>preach for Hire, and Divine for Money, and Proyheſie lyes unto the people;</hi> who chiefly <hi>ſeek for their gain from their quarter,</hi> and greedily hunt for the <hi>Golden Fleece,</hi> but profit not the Flock, but leave them as they found them, (if not worſe) <hi>ever learning, but never able to come to the knowledge of the Truth;</hi> if you will make Covenant with Death, and confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate with <hi>Amaleck</hi> in his cruel Conſpiracy againſt the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent; If you will be one with <hi>Haman</hi> in helping the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:135059:7"/>one to obtain the help of <hi>Caeſar</hi> againſt the Helpleſs; if you will involve your ſelves into that curſed League, and bind your ſelves (as it were) with an Oath againſt the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent; if you will be on the Serpent's ſide againſt the Seed of the Woman, and ſtrengthen the hands of the bloody She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pherds who ſeek to devour and woory Chriſt's ſheep; if you will give your Power to the falſe Prophet, and let him ride upon you, and make you his Vaſſels to afflict and torment the Innocent; if inſtead of helping the <hi>Woman</hi> againſt the <hi>Dragon,</hi> who is now caſting out the Floods of his Wrath and Miſchief againſt the Lambs of Chriſt, and help the <hi>old Dragon</hi> to caſt the harmleſs into naſty Holes, Caves and Priſons; If you will not quit your ſelves like men of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and ſhew your ſelves to be of a good underſtanding, fearing God, and hating Cruelty; If you will not look into the <hi>Royal Law of God,</hi> and <hi>do to us and all men, as you would have us and all men do to you:</hi> But if you will ſuffer us to fall into the hands of our Enemies, whoſe <hi>very mercies are cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elties,</hi> and you ſtand by, and rejoice at our Calamity: If you will not while you have <hi>Power,</hi> be a bridle to the Wicked, nor Rebuke this <hi>Exalted Spirit</hi> that ſeeks to Raiſe and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich it ſelf in the Ruines of the Lord's People, but give your Conſent and Countenance to the Wicked in their Cruelties againſt us; if you will ſtop your ears at the cry of the Righteous, and ſuffer our Adverſaries to oppreſs us all the day long, and plow great furrows upon our backs, and make our Afflictions grievous to be born.</p>
            <p>Then know this aſſuredly, The Lord will remember the afflictions of <hi>Joſeph;</hi> and though our Brethren ſell us into the hands of the <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> and intend our utter Ruine; though you and they in your ſecret Contrivances and Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations deviſe miſchief in your Beds againſt us, yet the Righteous God will not forſake us, he will ſtand by us in all our Troubles, and his bleſſing upon us, his preſence with us, his comfort to us, nor you, nor any Mortal can take from us. In all our ſufferings he is, and will be with us, and in his due time he will work Deliverance for us, and in the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:135059:8"/>mean he will ſupport us in all our Tribulations, he will fill our hearts with joy, when the hearts of the wicked ſhall faile them; he cannot forſake his own: He will fill us with Divine Wiſdom, and give us Courage to bear all the Wrongs and Injuries which the Wicked ſhall be ſuffered to lay upon us; He will Arm us ſufficiently with his Patience, and give us ſuch <hi>Spiritual Weapons</hi> as ſhall <hi>wound the Head</hi> and <hi>Heart</hi> of the <hi>Wicked:</hi> The innocency of our Sufferings ſhall kindle a Fire in the Hearts of our Adverſaries, that ſhall burn like an Oven, and ſhall not be quenched.</p>
            <p>The more you ſtrive to ſuppreſs the Truth by perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thoſe who live in it, the more ſhall Truth prevail and proſper: And if you ſhould ſeeke to fill all the Priſons in the Nation with us, or to take away that from us, which is not dear unto us, if the God of our Life require it of us; For <hi>We,</hi> our <hi>Life,</hi> our <hi>Goods,</hi> our <hi>All,</hi> is freely given up unto our God when he requires them of us. We can in his <hi>Strength</hi> glory over your <hi>Weakneſs,</hi> and in the hight of your Fury we fear you not: We know him to be with us, who is greater than he that is againſt us, and He will not faile us in the time of our greateſt need.</p>
            <p>That way you think to Raiſe your ſelves, and Ruine us, ſhall be the Ruine of your ſelves; that very Way ſhall Deliverance come out of <hi>Sion</hi> to the <hi>Captive SEED.</hi> For alas poor men! you ſtrive not onely againſt us, but you contend againſt your Maker; the <hi>God of Iſrael</hi> is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged with us, he Fights our Battels for us; for he is <hi>within us, then why ſhould we fear what man can do againſt us?</hi> Did ever any of <hi>Cain's Brood</hi> (you are no better who ere ye be, if you join with the <hi>Beaſt</hi> and <hi>falſe Prophet</hi> againſt the <hi>Lamb</hi>) proſper long in their afflicting of God's People? Why ſhould you wilfully throw away the <hi>Mercies</hi> of your <hi>Maker?</hi> Are you able to contend with him? Or did ever any ſtrive againſt him, that were not broken and confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by him?</p>
            <p>If you can pluck <hi>God Omnipotent</hi> &amp; <hi>Eternal</hi> from his <hi>Throne,</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:135059:8"/>and <hi>raze his Witneſs</hi> out of your <hi>own hearts,</hi> &amp; utterly <hi>extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh his ſearching, ſhining Light</hi> in your <hi>own,</hi> and the <hi>Peoples Conſciences;</hi> Then may you go on in your perſecuting of the Saints, and challenge the <hi>Peace of God</hi> to be your <hi>Portion:</hi> But if not, What is <hi>Man</hi> that he ſhould <hi>Vye</hi> thus with his <hi>Maker?</hi> Therefore be perſwaded yet while the <hi>Light of God</hi> does ſhine in your hearts, to be guided by it; leaſt for your diſobedience to it, the <hi>Lord God Omnipotent,</hi> the <hi>Lyon of the Tribe of Judah,</hi> (who now ſuffers as a <hi>Lamb within you</hi>) Ariſe in his fury, and put on Strength; If he Roar out of <hi>Sion,</hi> he wil make all the Beaſts in the Field to Tremble, he will be dreadful to the Wicked. If you perſiſt in your Impenitency, Cruelty and hard heartedneſs, and ſeek to dye your ſelves in the Blood of the Innocent—Then Know this aſſuredly from the Lord, <hi>The Righteous God will viſit you for your Iniquity, the <hi>Blood-thirſty Men ſhall not live out half their dayes:</hi> A ſhort work will the Lord make in the Earth; <hi>Vengeance, Vengeance</hi> from the <hi>Lord God,</hi> ſhall <hi>ſpeedily</hi> overtake you, though we forgive you, and never lift up a hand againſt you, The Dreadful God in his Terrible Wrath. will be avenged on you, you ſhall all ſurely ſurely periſh, both YOU and your KING.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>The <hi>LORD</hi> hath ſpoken it.</q>
            <p>O that Men would yet let the Fear of God take place in their hearts, it would Deliver them out of the Snares of the <hi>Cunning Hunter,</hi> who continually <hi>goes about like a Roar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Lyon, ſeeking whom he may devour.</hi> O that men would once learn to be wiſe, and ceaſe from their Worldly Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and ſeek after God's pure Wiſdome, which is only found and obtained in the Light. Surely they might do wel to take heed unto his Light which ſhines in their hearts, which ſecretly reproves all the Deeds of Darkneſſe, And would draw them from <hi>Iniquity</hi> unto <hi>Holineſs;</hi> from <hi>Pride,</hi> into <hi>pure Humility;</hi> and from under <hi>the Power of Satan, unto God:</hi> But this is the Miſery and Condemnation of the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:135059:9"/>World, <hi>That Light is come into the world, and men love <hi>Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> rather <hi>than Light,</hi> becauſe their Deeds are evil.</hi> 'Tis but now, as it was ever; The <hi>Seed of the Serpent</hi> cannot love, or be at peace with the <hi>Seed of Life;</hi> for <hi>Truth</hi> ever bears its Teſtimony againſt the World, <hi>That the Wayes, Cuſtoms, Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Traditions thereof, are evil:</hi> And that's the reaſon why the <hi>Heathens rage,</hi> and the cauſe of the Enmity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the two Seeds, even from the time of Righteous <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel,</hi> to this day. Search the Scriptures, and there you may find plentiful proof of this true Aſſertion.</p>
            <p>Never did the Light of the Goſpel ſince the Primitive Times, ſhine in more purity than now it does. Never had the Lord a people ſince the dayes of the Apoſtles, who walked more innocently and inoffenſively as to God and Man, than he hath raiſed up, and manifeſted in this Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration; And never did any people, who made ſo large a Profeſſion of God and Godlineſs, as the Prieſts and Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors do at this day, that ever manifeſted more Enmity, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice and Oppoſition againſt the Innocent for the <hi>Hat</hi> and <hi>Knee, Thee</hi> and <hi>Thou,</hi> and ſuch like things, than theſe men do at this day. Oh wonderful! That men who pretend to ſuch a hight of Profeſſion, ſhould be ſo dark, ſo ſottiſh, and have ſo little underſtanding in the <hi>Myſteries of God's King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> at this time of the Day, when Truth hath gained ſo much ground in the Nation, as all the ſtrength of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt</hi> ſhall not be able to recover one foot thereof from the Lamb and his true Followers in the Warfare againſt the Beaſt. Oh! I am wounded, I am wounded to ſee the Wickedneſs of the Wicked, to ſee the Beaſt and falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet boaſt it ſelf in its own ſtrength, and thus triumphing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exalt his Horn againſt the Heritage of God, and vaunt as if he were not to be moved; to ſee the undermining ſubtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the old Serpent, ſeeking the Lives of all the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cents in theſe Nations, onely becauſe <hi>Truth</hi> cannot feed <hi>Deceit,</hi> nor put into the Mouth of the falſe Prophet, but reproves ſin in the Gate, and makes Spiritual War againſt the Man of Sin; becauſe in the living Power and Authority
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:135059:9"/>of the Eternal God, it reproves Pride, Covetouſneſs, Luſt Wantonneſs, Swearing, Revenge, and makes war againſt the <hi>Drunkards of Ephraim:</hi> Becauſe it upholds not the Devil's Kingdom for term of life, but preaches up the Hope of Glory, the Power of the Living God in his People to be all-ſufficient to deſtroy and put an end to the Divels works; this makes the Divels roar, and increaſes the rage of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt and his Adherents againſt the followers of the Lamb, and makes the Brats of Pride gnaw their very tongues for Madneſs, becauſe the Sons of Meekneſs dare not in awe to God bow to that exalted Spirit, or feed the Beaſt with flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering titles.</p>
            <p>Tell me you that are well read in Hiſtories, if ever you found any Pagans or Chriſtians (ſo termed) ſince the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the world, that ever perſecuted an <hi>Innocent people</hi> for wearing their <hi>upper Garment,</hi> which God hath given them to be <hi>a Covering for their Head;</hi> and for uſing the <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage,</hi> which <hi>Chriſt, the lip of Truth,</hi> and all his <hi>Lambs</hi> ever uſed one to another; yea, which all Nations under the Heaven, in the <hi>Rudiments of Teaching,</hi> uſe for a <hi>Foundation.</hi> O that men ſhould be ſo void of the Fear and Dread of the Living God, as to ſuffer their hearts to be ſo filled with fury againſt the harmleſs Flock, who lifts not up a carnal wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon againſt their enemies! What is your meaning to hatch this Miſchief againſt them, thus earneſtly, to feek ſo ſubtilly to deſtroy them.</p>
            <p>What evil, Ah! what evil (O thou Enemy to the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous God) do'ſt thou know by his Lambs. In the fear of the Lord I challenge thee to declare it to them, if thou canſt, either in <hi>Doctrine, Life,</hi> or <hi>Converſation.</hi> How often have thy dreaming Prieſts attempted to impeach the one, and the Serpents eye watched over them for the other. And how often have they been foiled, and their eies even failed and grown dim, and wearied themſelves with their watching for our halting; How hath the righteous God confounded their wiſdom, and driven it backward, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:135059:10"/>powred ſhame and contempt upon them for their portion. How many have periſhed in their fooliſh expectation of the Fall of the Righteous! How often, yea how wonderfully hath the Lord ſtopt the mouths of theſe greedy dumb dogs, who never have enough, and ſilenced both Prieſt and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, Profeſſors and Proſane, even by his Babes and Suck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, who are nouriſht at the breaſts of his conſolation, and drink at the water of life freely, and can now no longer like fooliſh children dabble in the dirty Pools of the pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Prieſts of the Nation, nor buy their lying merchandizes any more. So that now for want of juſt matter of accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt them, they are fain to flye to their old Refuge of Lyes, ſubtil Inventions, falſe Accuſations, to enſnare the Innocent touching the things of their God, wherein the Serpent knows they dare not violate the Law of their God in the leaſt, or act the Hypocrite's part, to ſave his Head, and loſe his Soul: And therefore they run to their rotten Laws
<note n="*" place="margin">Oaths of Allegiance and Supremacy, Oath of Abjuration.</note>, never conſtituted by God, nor approved of by Man who lives in his fear, to be a Snare to the honeſt-hearted: And would but you Rulers of this Nation do to theſe Innocent Ones, as you could have all men do to you, the perſecuting Seed would not for theſe things harm one Saint. But the Will of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous God is worthy to be done, who in his due time will ſweep away the Refuge of Lyes, which the Wicked one fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers upon Chriſt's Flock.</p>
            <p>Haſt not thou O <hi>ENGLAND,</hi> in the time of thy late Troubles, had large Experience of the Innocency of theſe People? Have they ever had a hand in any Plots or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies againſt thy Governors? (though often falſly accuſed:) Let God's Witneſs ariſe, and it vvill give in true Evidence on the behalf of the Innocent; for I bear them record in the Name of the Lord, They are a harmleſs and a peaceable People, (thoſe called <hi>QUAKERS,</hi> vvho live in
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:135059:10"/>the life of Truth profeſſed by them) and ſeeks not the life of any, nor deſires any harm in their hearts to their very Enemies:</p>
            <p>They cannot confederate, nor never could (ſince they came into the life of the Lamb) with this or that part a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any Government; but were ever counted as Sheep for the Slaughter, and many of them have deeply ſuffered for Conſcience-ſake; as is ſufficiently known to many thouſands in the Nation; but more now of late than ever.</p>
            <p>O <hi>England! England!</hi> Art thou ſo drunk with Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, ſo blinded with mad Zeal, Art thou grown ſo fond of <hi>Romiſh</hi> Trumperies, that thou wilt needs quarrel and fall out with thy ſureſt friends, and not be ſatisfied without the blood of the Innocent? I bear them record, they are the choiceſt, the very beſt of thy real Friends, and the pureſt Gold that is current in thy Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Canſt thou not bear with the tenderneſs of their Conſciences? There is not a people in the Nation (I am bold to ſpeak it) that would ſo freely give to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration to tender Conſciences, as they would do: Thou alloweſt ſome Grains (I well know) to thy Gold; and why not a little lawful Liberty to a truly tender Conſcience? Why wilt thou offer to urge an Oath upon them? God's Witneſs in all Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences knows their <hi>yea</hi> and <hi>nay</hi> is as binding unto them, as all the Oaths and Bonds of the beſt of thy Inhabitants beſide them. And why doſt thou, O <hi>Supream Power,</hi> impriſon, or ſuffer any to be impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned or diſquieted for working in their Calling up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe called Saints dayes? Is this the Toleration thou intendeſt to allow to tender Conſciences? O!
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:135059:11"/>What's become of the Word of a King?</p>
            <p>And tell me now, O ye men in Authority, and all ſober-minded people, if Paſſion be down, and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice removed: What is that O man, in thee (what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever thou art) high or low, rich or poor, that is offended becauſe the honeſt-hearted bows not with his body to it, or ſtands not bare without his Hat before it? Or frets and fumes like a Fool, or a Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low new come out of <hi>Bedlam,</hi> if a man do but ſpeak proper <hi>Engliſh</hi> to him, <hi>Thee</hi> or <hi>Thou</hi> to a ſingle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon?</p>
            <p>Is it the Babe of Humility, or the Seed of Pride that is ſo ſoon puft up into paſsion, that ſometimes to an affectionate kind word, it anſwers diſcourte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly with blows or buffetings?</p>
            <p>Oh <hi>England! England!</hi> When wilt thou come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Humility? When will thy Malice ceaſe againſt the Innocent, and thy ſurious folly finde an end? When wilt thou leave perſecuting thy own Bowels?</p>
            <p>Not ſo long as the Beaſt and falſe Prophet have Dominion over thee; not till the Righteous God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waken thee with his Judgements: And verily O <hi>England,</hi> 'tis time that thy Governors knew, thou ripens faſt, thou art fattening for Deſtruction, while thou licks up that which formerly thou vomited, and canſt now conform (though with gripings in thy Conſcience) to Popery and Popiſh Prelates, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute the Saints in Priſon for not ſubmitting to thy Popiſh Feſtivals.</p>
            <p>Oh whither are you wheeling, you great Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors of the Kingdom! O <hi>England, England!</hi> wouldſt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:135059:11"/>thou not even drink the very dregs of Popery, if the Lord would try thee? But he hath a Cup for thee to drink, which will awaken thee, he hath Arrows in his Quiver that will wound thee to the heart, and lay thy perſecuting Head-pieces in the Duſt, though the Innocent lift not a hand againſt them.</p>
            <p>The Righteous God will plead the Cauſe of his People, he will ſuddenly ſmite the ſtiff-necked and ſtout-hearted, that ſay of his Son, the Light of the World, <hi>Nolumus hunc Regnare, we will not have this man to Rule over us;</hi> He will make the fat Bulls of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhan</hi> Roar; he will make the Beaſt feeble in his ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>news, yea as weak as water.</p>
            <p>Down goes the Beaſt and the blind Guides toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; they that are willing to be deluded by them, who make war againſt the Innocent: An irrecover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able wound ſhall the Wicked receive, and then ſhall they know the evil they have done in outſtanding the day of their Viſitation, and helping on the miſeries and afflictions of God's People.</p>
            <q>UNto Thee, O Lord God Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent, do we commit our Cauſe; Thou Lord knoweſt the Integrity of thy Choſen ones; Thou ſees we have no other help in Heaven but thee, and that there is none in all the Earth from
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:135059:12"/>whom we can expect deliverance, but from Thee, Thy Mercies are ſure to thy Righteous Seed, and thy Compaſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons can never fail, nor be ſeparated from it:
<q>This is our Stay, this is our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, O thou God of all Conſolation, thou art with us, thy Love is to us, thy Preſence is amongſt us, and thy All-ſufficient power is felt and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed within us: Thy everlaſting loving kindneſs (which compaſſes us about) no mortals can take from us. Glory, glory, unto Sion's King for ever.</q>
            </q>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Lincolne</hi> 
                  <date>the 7th day of the 11th Month, called, <hi>January.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>M. M.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:135059:12"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
